<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</origin>
        <pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
        <title>ABM_RangeEstimated20100806</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Alabama Beach Mouse Habitat Range Map - Modified</abstract>
      <purpose>This Layer is to provide the public and other agencies information on where the range of the ABM is believed to be as of the date the layer was created. This particular layer is a modification of the original ABM habitat maps for EPA use only.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.028708</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.631486</eastbc>
        <northbc>30.258848</northbc>
        <southbc>30.222871</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Alabama Beach Mouse</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>US Fish and Wildlife information is only for the intended use of the individual or organization who requested it and may not be transferred to or used by any other party. Any material supplied from the database, including database subsets and accompanying files, may not be distributed in any way without the consent of the USFWS. If data is acquired through a data license, use of the data is subject to the terms of the license agreement developed between the USFWS and the information requestor.</accconst>
    <useconst>This layer was created for the EPA to publish on its pesticide website. This layer was created by the U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service (USFWS) to geographically depict what is believed, as of the date of the map, to be the habitat range of the endangered Alabama Beach Mouse (ABM). It was created as a general resource tool for use by the USFWS, and is not intended to be a definitive indicator concerning the presence or absence of ABM on any particular site. Changes in USFWS’s knowledge about ABM presence in particular areas are constantly occurring. New information will be used by the USFWS in work related to administration of the Endangered Species Act. This layer will be updated on a regular basis to reflect the most current available information. The presence of ABM on any particular site is best determined by the completion of a trapping survey by a qualified biologist holding a valid scientific collection permit. No warranty, expressed or implied, is made by the USFWS as to the accuracy of information contained herein. Questions should be addressed to the Alabama Field Office of the USFWS at 251-441-5181.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>US Fish &amp; Wildlife Service</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1208 Main St.</address>
          <city>Daphne</city>
          <state>AL</state>
          <postal>36526</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>251-441-5181</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>251-441-6222</cntfax>
        <cntemail>Alabama@fws.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native> Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1.4959</native>
  </idinfo>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>244</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 16N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-87.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
            <ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>ABM_RangeEstimated20100806</enttypl>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Historic_H</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Leng</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Perimeter</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Area</attrlabl>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20180920</metd>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>