<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.dtd">-->
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20061002</CreaDate><CreaTime>10002300</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><ModDate>20061005</ModDate><ModTime>10015500</ModTime><MetaID>{78D14B38-75F9-40AD-9A53-1A3B011C4029}</MetaID></Esri><idinfo><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg><cntper>Larry Handley</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Principal Investigator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8691</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax><cntemail>larry_handley@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><accconst>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the distributor described above or from another USGS server and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. The distributor makes no claim as to the data's suitability for other purposes.</accconst><useconst>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center as a data source would be appreciated in products developed from these data, and such acknowledgement as is standard for citation and legal practices for data source is expected by users of these data. Sharing new data layers developed directly from these data would be appreciated by U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center staff. Users should be aware that comparison with other data sets for the same area from other time periods may be inaccurate due to inconsistencies resulting from changes in mapping conventions, data collection procedures, and computer processes over time. The distributor shall not be liable for improper or incorrect use of these data, based on the description of appropriate/inappropriate uses described in this metadata document. These data are not legal documents and are not to be used as such</useconst><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</origin><pubdate>200610</pubdate><title>Baldwin County, AL 2001 Habitat Data (polygons)</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace><publish>USGS, NWRC</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><keywords><theme><themekey>habitat</themekey><themekey>wetlands</themekey><themekey>uplands</themekey><themekey>photointerpretation</themekey><themekey>Cowardin Classification</themekey><themekey>Anderson Classification</themekey><themekey>mapping</themekey><themekey>GIS</themekey><themekey>7.5 minute</themekey><themekey>quadrangle</themekey><themekey>map</themekey><themekey>marsh</themekey><themekey>restoration</themekey><themekey>protection</themekey><themekey>coastal</themekey><themekey>cartography</themekey><themekt>none</themekt><themekey>scanning</themekey></theme><place><placekey>Alabama</placekey><placekey>AL</placekey><placekey>Baldwin County</placekey><placekey>South Alabama</placekey><placekey>Barrineau Park</placekey><placekey>Bay Minette North</placekey><placekey>Bay Minette South</placekey><placekey>Bilbo Island</placekey><placekey>Blacksher</placekey><placekey>Bon Secour Bay</placekey><placekey>Bridgehead</placekey><placekey>Carlton</placekey><placekey>Chrysler</placekey><placekey>Daphne</placekey><placekey>Dogwood Creek</placekey><placekey>Dyas</placekey><placekey>Elberta</placekey><placekey>Elsanor</placekey><placekey>Enon</placekey><placekey>Foley</placekey><placekey>Freemanville</placekey><placekey>Fort Morgan</placekey><placekey>Gateswood</placekey><placekey>Gulf Shores</placekey><placekey>Hurricane</placekey><placekey>Lillian</placekey><placekey>Little Point Clear</placekey><placekey>Magnolia Springs</placekey><placekey>McCullough</placekey><placekey>Mobile</placekey><placekey>Orange Beach</placekey><placekey>Perdido Bay</placekey><placekey>Pine Beach</placekey><placekey>Point Clear</placekey><placekey>Robertsdale</placekey><placekey>Seminole</placekey><placekey>Silver Hill</placekey><placekey>St. Andrews Bay</placekey><placekey>Stapleton</placekey><placekey>Steelwood Lake</placekey><placekey>Stiggins Lake</placekey><placekey>Tensaw</placekey><placekey>The Basin</placekey><placekey>Vaughn</placekey><placekey>Walnut Hill</placekey><placekt>None</placekt></place></keywords><descript><abstract>This data set consists of digital data (polygons) describing wetlands and uplands habitats for Baldwin County in South Alabama for the year 2001. Wetlands were classified using the Cowardin, et al., wetland classification scheme to the level of salinity modifiers. Uplands were classified using a customized classification scheme which can be cross-referenced to Anderson, et al.. The habitats were derived from interpretation of color infrared photography, mapped at 1:24,000. The Baldwin County project includes all 43 USGS (7.5 minute series) quadrangles located within the county line.</abstract><purpose>The intended use of this data set is to provide information to aid efforts in the conservation, restoration, creation, and enhancement of Alabama's coastal wetlands. The habitat data is used for an on going National Wetland Inventory project on time comparisons.</purpose></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2001</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>publication date</current></timeperd><spdom><bounding><westbc>-88.125</westbc><eastbc>-87.375</eastbc><northbc>31.375</northbc><southbc>30.125</southbc></bounding></spdom><crossref><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</origin><pubdate>200610</pubdate><title>Baldwin County 2001 Habitat Data (Linears)</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Lafayette, LA</pubplace><publish>USGS, NWRC</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></crossref><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status></idinfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8500</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax><cntpos>Web/Data Administrator</cntpos></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from a USGS server, and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata document associated with these data. U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data, including, without limitations, the implied warranties or merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose. Also, use of trade names or commerical products in these metadata is solely for the purpose of providing specific information, and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the U.S. Government. Any downloading and use of these data signifies a user's agreement to comprehension and compliance of the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center Standard Disclaimer. Insure all portions of metadata are read and clearly understood before using these data in order to protect both user and U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center interests.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ARCE</formname><formvern>9+</formvern><filedec>zipped</filedec></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://sabdata.nrwc.gov</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None, if available online</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg></cntorgp><cntpos>Metadata Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8500</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><metac>There are no access limitations on acquiring the metadata document. Metadata can be accessed through the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center website or the Federal Geographic Data Committee (FGDC) metadata clearinghouse</metac><metuc>Acknowledgement of the U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center as the metadata source would be appreciated. Please cite the original metadata when using portions of the record to create a similar record for slightly altered data for reprojection or subsetting.</metuc><metd>20061002</metd></metainfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20061005</mdDateSt><dataqual><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Baldwin County Planning Commission</origin><pubdate>2001</pubdate><title>Baldwin County Color Infrared Aerial Photography</title><geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Baldwin County, AL</pubplace><publish>Baldwin County Planning Commission</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></srccite><srctime><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate>20010216</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20010218</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20010219</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srcscale>36000</srcscale><typesrc>stable-base material</typesrc><srccitea>CIR</srccitea><srccontr>The primary data source for photo-interpretation and identification of habitat data.</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Larry Handley</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8691</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax><cntemail>larry_handley@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont><procdesc>Cartographic Process for the lower portion of the county- After acquiring aerial photography for the project area, stereo pairs were created and packaged according to the project boundaries. Maps for cartographic transformation were generated, using the same aerial photography, through means of rectification and mosaicking. The photos were interpreted using a Bausch and Lomb stereoscope at 10x magnification. Cartographic work was performed using a Zoom Transfer Scope, and magnification varied according to the scale of the source data (photography). All cartographic and photointerpretation processes adhere to National Wetlands Inventory (NWI) standards</procdesc><procdate>2006</procdate></procstep><procstep><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Larry Handley</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8691</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax><cntemail>larry_handley@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont><procdesc>Cartographic process for the upper portion of the county - Habitats were classified on-screen using ArcMap; data were attributed within ArcMap.</procdesc><procsv>ESRI ArcMap 9+</procsv><procdate>2006</procdate></procstep><procstep><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Steve Hartley</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Geographer</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>700 Cajundome Blvd</address><city>Lafayette</city><state>LA</state><postal>70506</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>337 266-8500</cntvoice><cntfax>337 266-8513</cntfax><cntemail>steve_hartley@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont><procdesc>Digital conversion for the lower portion of the county - The mylar-based, hard copy maps were scanned, georeferenced and vectorized at the US Geological Survey, National Wetlands Research Center using an Ideal FCS 8010 scanner, ArcGIS georeferencing module and ArcScan vector conversion software.</procdesc><procsv>ESRI ArcGIS 9+</procsv><procdate>2006</procdate></procstep></lineage><attracc><attraccr>The accuracy of the attributes is dependent on the expertise of the photointerpreter and the processes involved in converting the delineation to digital form. All work conducted by the photointerpreter is double-checked by another photointerpreter. Upon conversion to a digital form, an on-screen comparison with the hard copy data is performed. The accuracy of these data is believed to be high, although no formal assessment was done.</attraccr></attracc><logic>ArcGIS software is used to create and maintain topological relationships between features. Polygonal features begin and end at the same point, contain no overshoots or undershoots, and contain a single label. Linear features are continuous where appropriate, i.e., dangling arcs are removed if they are not required.</logic><complete>For the cartographic process (photointerpretation), accordance with nationally accepted mapping standards and conventions are followed. For the digital conversion process, conventions and standard check list methodologies in place for the time period were followed.
Two types of photointerpretation were used to generate these data, traditional and digitial. The lower portion of the county was photointerpreted using traditional methods (stereoscope, ZTS). The upper portion was photointerpreted using ArcMap. The upper portion consists of the following quadrangles: Cartlon, Chrysler, Tensaw, Blacksher, McCullough, Vaughn, Perdido, Freemanville, Bay Minette North, Dyas, Walnut Hill, Bay Minette South, Dogwood Creek, Enon, Stapleton, Steelwood Lake, Gateswood, Barrineau Park.   </complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The accuracy of the horizontal positions is based on the accuracy of the georeferenced data source (which can be USGS DOQQs, DEMS, flight line center points, and/or calibration reports). The sources used vary from project to project. All USGS Mapping products adhere to the National Mapping Accuracy Standard.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\BARBARELLA\D\Data\CNSMP2\bldwin_poly_01hab</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc></distorTran></distributor></distInfo><spdoinfo><indspref>Baldwin County</indspref><direct>Vector</direct></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>16</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer><longcm>-87.00</longcm><latprjo>0.0</latprjo><feast>50000.00</feast><fnorth>0.00</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.00</absres><ordres>0.00</ordres></coordrep><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.00</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><attr><attrlabl>FID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features. </udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>AREA</attrlabl><attrdef>The area of the polygon in coverage units</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS, NWRC</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><attrunit>coverage units</attrunit><rdommin>0.0</rdommin><rdommax>100000000000.00</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>PERIMETER</attrlabl><attrdef>The perimeter of the polygon</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS, NWRC</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><attrunit>coverage units</attrunit><rdommin>0.0</rdommin><rdommax>1000000.00</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>HABITAT</attrlabl><attrdomv><codesetd><codesetn>Cowardin, et al., Wetland Classification Scheme</codesetn><codesets>Cowardin, Lewis M., Virginia Carter, Francis Goblet, and Edward T. LaRoe. Classification of wetlands and deepwater habitats of the United States. U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. Biological Services Program; FWS/OBS - 79/31. 103 pp.</codesets></codesetd></attrdomv><attrdomv><codesetd><codesetn>Modified version of Anderson et al. Classification scheme for uplands</codesetn><codesets>Can be cross-referenced to Anderson, James R., Ernest E. Hardy, John T. Roach, and Richard T. Witmer. A Land Use and Land Cover Classification System for Use with Remote Sensor Data. Geological Survey Professional Paper 964. A revision of the land use classification system as presented in U.S. Geological Survey Circular 671. United States Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, USA</codesets></codesetd></attrdomv><attrdef>The wetland classification system is hierarchical, with wetlands and deepwater habitats divided among 5 major systems at the broadest level. The five systems include Marine, Estuarine, Riverine, lacustrine, and Palustrine. These systems are further divided into subsystems which reflect hydrologic conditions. Below the subsystems are classes and subclasses describing vegetation or substrate, and modifiers relating to hydrology, soils, water chemistry, and man's activities.</attrdef><attrdefs>Cowardin, Lewis M., Virginia Carter, Francis Goblet, and Edward T. LaRoe. Classification of wetlands and deepwater habitats of the United States. U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. Biological Services Program; FWS/OBS - 79/31. 103 pp. Customized classification which can be cross-referenced to Anderson, James R., Ernest E. Hardy, John T. Roach, and Richard T. Witmer. A Land Use and Land Cover Classification System for Use with Remote Sensor Data. Geological Survey Professional Paper 964. A revision of the land use classification system as presented in U.S. Geological Survey Circular 671. United States Government Printing Office, Washington: 1976.</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl><attrdef>The acres of each polygon</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS, NWRC</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><attrunit>acres</attrunit><rdommin>0.0</rdommin><rdommax>1000</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Hectares</attrlabl><attrdef>The hectares of each polygon</attrdef><attrdefs>USGS, NWRC</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.0</rdommin><attrunit>hectares</attrunit><rdommax>100</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><enttyp><enttypl>DATA</enttypl><enttypd>The attributed features of the habitat data</enttypd><enttypds>USGS, NWRC</enttypds></enttyp></detailed></eainfo></metadata>
