<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Thomas Strange, Covington Civil and Environmental , Sr. Scientist</origin>
        <pubdate>20170724</pubdate>
        <title>2017 Uplands Wetlands Habitat Mapping for Mobile and Baldwin Counties, AL </title>
        <geoform>map</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This data set consists of digital data describing wetlands and uplands habitats for Mobile and BaldwinCounty in South Alabama for the year 2016-2017. Wetlands were classified using the Cowardin, et al., wetland classification scheme to the modifier level. Uplands were classified using a customized classification scheme which can be cross-referenced to Anderson, et al.. The habitats were derived from interpretation of 1-meter color infrared photography flown by Quantum Spatial, The project includes one feature class dataset of Mobile and Badlwin Counties.</abstract>
      <purpose>The intended use of this data set is to provide information to aid MBNEP and other agencies with efforts in the conservation, restoration, and enhancement of  coastal wetlands in Mobile and Baldwin Counties, AL. </purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20160229</begdate>
          <enddate>20170731</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>This data set represents the extent of wetlands  habitats that were deterined by the use of 1-m, 4 band,  NIR remotely sensed data, The accuracy of image interpretation depends on the quality of the imagery, the experience of the image analysts, the amount and quality of the collateral data, and the amount of ground truth verification work conducted. There is a margin error inherent in the use of imagery, thus detailed on-the-ground inspection of any particular site, may result in revision of the wetland boundaries or classification, established through image analysis. Wetlands or other mapped features may have changed since the date or the imagery and/or field work. There may be occasional differences in polygon boundaries or classifications between the information depicted on the map and the actual conditions on site.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Unknown</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-88.407370</westbc>
        <eastbc>-87.388630</eastbc>
        <northbc>30.818195</northbc>
        <southbc>30.227119</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Habitat</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Wetlands, Cowardin Classification, Uplands, Anderson Classification, Coastal, Restoration, Protection, GIS,</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
        <themekey>planningCadastre</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <datacred>This project was supported by the Mobile Bay National Estuary Program. </datacred>
    <native> Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1.4959</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Along with the associated topological attributes, the main attribute in this data set is the Habitat - This is the habitat classification for the area (to include polygonal and linear features). Wetlands are lands transitional between terrestrial and aquatic systems where the water table is usually at or near the surface of the land is covered by shallow water. Uplands are terrestrial systems that do not exhibit wetland characteristics. The wetland classification system is hierarichial, with wetlands and deepwater habitats divided among 5 major systems at the broadest level. The five system include Marine, Estuarine, Riverine, Lacustrine, and Palustrine. These systems are further divided into subsystems which reflect hydrologic conditions. Below the subsystems are classes and subclasses describing vegetation or substrate, and modifiers relating to hydrology, soils, water chemistry, and man's activities.</attraccr>
      <qattracc>
        <attracce>The accuracy of the attributes is dependent on the expertise of the photointerpreter and the processes involved in converting the delineation to digital form. All work conducted by the photointerpreter is double-checked by another photointerpreter. 
For the cartographic process (photointerpretation), accordance with nationally accepted mapping standards and conventions are followed. For the digital conversion process, conventions and standard check list methodologies in place for the time period were followed.</attracce>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The fidelity of the relationships in the data set were tested and validated by topology validation tools within ESRI.</logic>
    <complete>This dataset may be continually updated in various areas where wetlands data are added to the wetlands data layer from the USFWS, MBNEP, or other federal, state and local agencies, tribes, non-governmental organizations and universities.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <typesrc>hardDisk</typesrc>
        <srccontr>
For the cartographic process (photointerpretation), accordance with nationally accepted mapping standards and conventions are followed. For the digital conversion process, conventions and standard check list methodologies in place for the time period were followed.
</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Accuracy Assessment: We utilized an ArcGIS tool suite (Spatial Analyst &gt; Classification and Segmentation) that created a random set of points across the study area, allowed us to ‘ground truth’ those points, and compared them to the classification at each area.  We chose a stratified random sampling strategy that generates a set of points that is randomly distributed throughout each class, where each class has a number of points proportional to its relative areas.  We began by generating 700 random points.  We also appended an additional 300 points that validated by the field surveys conducted in 2016.

The final accuracy report generated an observed accuracy 89.86%.  The Kappa Coefficient was 88.55%. The Kappa coefficient expresses the proportionate reduction in error generated by a classification process compared with the error of a completely random classification. For example, the Kappa statistic cited here implies that the classification process is avoiding 88.55% of the errors that a completely random classification would generate.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20170731</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
              <cntorg>Radiance Technologies/Covington Civil Engineering </cntorg>
              <cntper>GIS Analyst</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>GIS/RS Analyst </cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
              <city>Stennis</city>
              <state>MS</state>
              <postal>39529</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>228-396-0486</cntvoice>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>GT-polygon composed of chains</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1155</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 16N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-87.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.0001</absres>
            <ordres>0.0001</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>IntertidalMarshesFlatsTrial</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Polygon data describing wetlands and uplands habitats for Mobile and Baldwin County </enttypd>
        <enttypds>ESRI </enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Numeric </edomv>
            <edomvd>Geometry</edomvd>
            <edomvds>ESRI </edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>habitat</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Cowardin et al. 1979 Habitat Classification code</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text Code</edomv>
            <edomvd>Habitat Class Code</edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>system</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The structure of this classification is hierarchical, progressing from Systems and Subsystems, at the most general levels, to Classes, Subclasses, Modifier</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>System Class Code</edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>subsystem</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The structure of this classification is hierarchical, progressing from Systems and Subsystems, at the most general levels, to Classes, Subclasses, Modifiers. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Subsystem Class Code</edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>class</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The structure of this classification is hierarchical, progressing from Systems and Subsystems, at the most general levels, to Classes, Subclasses, Modifiers. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Habitat Class Code </edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>subclass</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The structure of this classification is hierarchical, progressing from Systems and Subsystems, at the most general levels, to Classes, Subclasses, Modifiers. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Subclass Habiat Code</edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>modifier</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Modifiers for water regime are applied to Classes, Subclasses, and Dominance Types. Special modifiers describe wetlands and deepwater habitats that have been either created or highly modified by man. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI </attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Text</edomv>
            <edomvd>Modifier Habiat Code, as applicable</edomvd>
            <edomvds>MBNEP </edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20180918</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Radiance Technologies </cntorg>
          <cntper>Joy Parikh </cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>GIS Program Lead</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
          <address>Building 1103</address>
          <city>Stennis Space Center</city>
          <state>MS</state>
          <postal>39529</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>601-918-2954</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>joy.parikh@radiancetech.com</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metuc>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the distributor, MBNEP, described in the distribution section of this metadata record or from another USGS server and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. The distributor makes no claim as to the data's suitability for other purposes.</metuc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>